Greene Smith Papers
Greene Smith Papers
1860-1907
Smith, Greene, 1841-1880.
2.5 linear ft.
Son of New York reformer, philanthropist and abolitionist Gerrit Smith, much involved in ornithology. Collection contains correspondence, financial material, ornithological material, miscellany.
2751615
Biographical History
Greene Smith (1841-1880) was a son of New York reformer, philanthropist and abolitionist Gerrit Smith. An avid amateur scientist, Smith was very interested in ornithology and taxidermy. In 1863 he built a three-story museum to house his collection of bird specimens, many of which eventually went to Cornell (where Smith lectured as professor of ornithology), Harvard, or Colgate University.
A genealogy of the Smith family is available here (if online) or at the end of this finding aid (if in hard copy).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Greene Smith Papers contains correspondence, financial material, ornithological material and miscellany.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Financial material is subdivided by type and within that arranged chronologically. The remaining series are arranged alphabetically by topic or type.
Related Material
has the papers of several members of the Smith family. See also the following:
Gerrit Smith Papers
Peter Smith Papers
Gerrit Smith Miller Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874.; Smith, Greene, 1841-1880.; Smith, Peter, 1768-1837.; Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1822-1911.; Miller, Gerrit Smith, 1845-1937.; Birds -- Taxidermy.; Ornithologists -- United States.; Ornithology -- Research.; Ornithology -- Study and teaching.; Catalogs (documents); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Receipts (financial records); Ornithologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - General, 1860-1878; 28 folders (Box 1)
  - General, 1879-1892; 9 folders (Box 2)
  - General, undated (Box 2)
  - Smith, Gerrit (father), 1851-1853; 1872-1873 (Box 2)
  - Other family relatives (Box 2)
  - Miller, Elizabeth Smith, 1874-1877 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Gerrit Smith, 1875-1878; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Smith, Ann C. (mother), 1868; 1873 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Bessie (wife) (Box 2)
  - Smith, Bessie (wife), 1873-1907; 10 folders (Box 3)
- Financial material
  - Bank deposit acknowledgements, Henry Clews and Co., New York, 1871-1873 (Box 3)
  - Bank statements, Henry Clews and Co., New York, 1871-1873 (Box 3)
  - Accounts and miscellaneous financial documents, 1873-1878 (Box 3)
  - Bills and receipts, 1860; 1863,; 1868-1872 (Jun); 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Bills and receipts, 1872 (Jul)-1903; 18 folders (Box 4)
  - Bills and receipts, undated (Box 4)
  - Drafts, 1868-1879; 16 folders (Box 5)
  - Promissory notes, 1871-1872 (Box 5)
- Ornithological material
  - Bird dealers' itemized bills, 1869-1879; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bird dealers' catalogs, undated (Box 5)
  - Catalog of birds, eggs and nests, Greene Smith Museum, Peterboro, New York, 11 Jul 1880 (Box 5)
  - Egg and nest description forms of G. H. Ragsdale, 1878 (Box 5)
  - List of eggs arrived from John Krider, undated (Box 5)
  - Notes by Greene Smith on orders placed with bird dealers (Box 5)
- Miscellanea
  - Diary fragments, 4-14 Mar 1887 [?] (Box 5)
  - Comments by Greene Smith on O. B. Frothingham's biography of Gerrit Smith, 2 Jan 1878 (Box 5)
  - Estate of Green Smith, envelope that once contained his will, dated in his hand June 24, 1880; letters testamentary naming Elizabeth F. Smith and Gerrit Smith as executors (Box 5)
  - Genealogical record, possibly of the FitzHugh family, 18th c. (Box 5)
  - Hunting permit issued to Greene Smith, France, 24 Oct 1861 (Box 5)
  - Legal material, 1875-1881 (Box 5)
  - Notes, 1872; undated; includes undated note in Gerrit Smith's handwriting (Box 5)
  - Passport of Greene Smith, signed by Charles Francis Adams, 1861 (Box 5)